You can make business decisions very
differently if your goal is to be a very
profitable or a very fast growing
company for two years versus if you want
to build a company for that will be
around in 100 years. That's what a lot
of premium apps fall into this premium
trap where the easiest win you can
always do is like oh yeah let me take
some free just make it paid and
immediately all your metrics are green
and that does kind of work for 6 months
or maybe a year but eventually it stops
working. Preserving the free value is
just a moat that we have to keep and we
want to keep for missionary reasons, but
for business reasons it also makes a lot
of sense. Hello, I'm your host David
Bernard. My guest today is Jim Canu,
chief product officer at Dualingo. On
the podcast, I talk with Jim about the
premium trap many apps fall into, why
free trials work even for premium
products, and how try for $0 and0
actually outperforms try for free. Hey
Jim, thanks so much for joining me on
the podcast today.
>> Happy to be here. Excited to chat.
>> So, I wanted to talk through Duelingo's
monetization story. I mean, few apps out
there are going to have tens of millions
of users and being in the position
Duolingo was in when you started
monetizing. But I think there's so much
to learn from the lessons y'all learned
along the way. So, let's talk about
that. Duallingingo was a free app,
famously completely free, and then the
first step was layering on ads. It was
actually was a website. It was not a
mobile app. And this website's idea was
actually to be completely free. there
would be actually no monetization for
the users that are using Duolingo to
learn a language. However, as users did
exercises to learn a language, which
includes a lot of translation. So, if
you're learning Spanish, a lot of your
exercises you're translating Spanish to
English or English to Spanish, users
would do these exercises to learn, but
there would be a crowdsource model to
collect those translations and
eventually turn that into a translation
service. Uh we actually did this like
this was built uh
>> so I heard the story but I didn't know
you actually
>> this was built this was this went live
and it actually generated some revenue
even though very small uh so we would do
thing we would have customers that are
like at the time like the big news
outlets as well like CNN Buzzfeed they
would feed an article they wanted to
translate from English to Spanish and
then our our users in bits and pieces
would translate that article and we
would crowdsource a translated article
and then provide a a uh a translated
article back uh to CNN. It it was
actually a genius model. If you want to
do something crowdsourced, it's actually
you you're kind of serving both sides a
a a positive value. The challenge with
that model was though is is twofold. One
of them is translation also this is
prelims like translation now has changed
a lot post LLM but this is you have to
remember this is 2013 as well. Even then
translation was a race to the bottom
business model. So if we were providing
a service for I don't know how 3 cents,
10 cents, $3, whatever it is, uh there
was always somebody else trying to do it
for a little cheaper by having someone
in the Philippines translate it for
cheaper. So there's always a race to the
bottom. It is hard to scale for that
reason. And then number two is more
fundamental, which is the translation
quality of a language learner is
actually not great. So you end up
putting practices in place to uplevel
the quality of that translation which
then you turn into a basically a
translation business and it really start
shifting your resources towards
basically translation and not teaching.
>> Uh so we realized it had these these
these problems and around the time I
joined Dualingo which was 2016 we had
pivoted away from that model and was
trying to figure out what the next model
should be. Actually our very very first
experiment with anything monetization
was the streak repair as an inapp
purchase and around the same time the
ads experiment started but I think the
first thing that users saw at Dualingo
as like a thing they could buy was uh
repairing your streak for I think a
dollar or $3. That was our first entry.
It was honestly it was a good
experiment. We actually learned a lot.
We learned that users really cared about
their streak and some uh a good
percentage of our users are willing to
pay a dollar or two to uh repair their
broken streak. But then I think then we
get we got into this experiment mode of
what really works with our audience and
how do we make sure that we keep the
product highly retentive and a great
user experience. Uh coming back to your
questions that is the moment where we
started trying ads. So that was 2016. Um
it's funny if you launched if you go
watch and I think these talks are still
out there. Our co-founder CEO Luis gave
these talks for Dualingo launch and he
said we will never have ads, never inapp
purchases and never subscriptions and
those are the exact three things that I
built in that order basically. And the
reason he was so adamant in saying those
was we dueling's mission is basically
centered around providing access to
education. And at the time every
education business model whatever they
did they would lock the education value
behind the pay wall get someone to pay.
Think about the Rosetta Stone model for
example that was the very standard model
at the time where you're selling
content. We never wanted to be that, but
I think we realized there's actually a
way to build do that, which is provide
access to education, but also monetize
the bells and whistles. That's why we
set on this premium journey. Ads fits
into that really nicely. If done well,
users don't have to pay you anything,
but you can actually generate some
revenue. So, ads was that test.
Honestly, testing ads wasn't rocket
science. It was fairly easy to test our
way into of course making sure the user
experience is great, but also how do you
maximize revenue from ads while making
sure your retention remains awesome. The
hardest part I would say was the
cultural shift of going from a
pre-monetization app to a
post-monetization app because until
then, so until the time I joined, there
was like 60ish employees. I think a lot
of folks joined the company thinking it
was maybe even an like a nonprofit like
mission because the mission is so grand
and so awesome and the company never
quite bothered to think about revenue
and monetization very much. It was a
mind shift to to the company to be hey
there's things we have to do so we can
generate revenue and if we generate
revenue we can actually fund our mission
so that we can be more impactful was
probably the hardest part of turning on
ads on Dualingo.
>> Yeah. And I I guess you weren't there at
this time, but I did hear a there's a
story out there around a venture
capitalist pushing this direction. What
what's the story there?
>> So this story I think is is when uh
Capital G invested in Dualingo, Leila,
who was also on our board after that
investment for a while, she told Luis at
the time, "This is probably the last
investor uh you will have in this
company before you figure out
monetization." And so in a rounded way
to say you have to figure out
monetization as a growing company you at
some point have to do that but I think
also the common wisdom at the time for
consumer companies like Facebook is like
just grow audience you'll figure out
monetization later. So I think dueling
followed that but until a point where I
think capital G and and Leila had this
big push to be uh okay uh it's time and
uh I I guess that was around 2016. So
when I joined the mindset shift has has
had moved to and Luis's like first thing
he told me was like we hired you your
sole job is to figure out how to
monetize Dualingo. Uh and and that's
that's what I tried to figure out.
>> That's awesome. What a great story. So
ads
that they're tricky. How did you
introduce ads? one in a way that didn't
totally piss off users and tank
retention and I mean I'm sure there was
user push back and bad reviews in the
app store. This is part of the story I
think a lot of folks can learn from
because any monetization change you make
will spur some level of like bad reviews
or negative feedback or churn. So h how
did you balance that as you started to
roll ads into the product?
>> This is a very good question. I think
that there's the I'll give the obvious
answers and maybe the harder to navigate
parts. First, for a consumer product,
you should obviously dog food your
product heavily. So, so that whatever
you're doing to the experience, you have
firsthand experience on how it feels.
Meaning, you can easily say, "Oh, we'll
put an app open ad." And if you're just
watching metrics, I'm sure that might
look fine, but when you test it, you're
like, "What the hell is this?" Then you
should know what you've introduced and
obviously avoid the things that you
wouldn't want to see as a user. Hence
our first test and honestly kind of even
today that's our only ad placement is
after you've computed a lesson we show
you an ad. Now not during not before but
always after because we believe that
doesn't interrupt your learning. So one
is the qualitative. It should be a good
user experience and you should know that
by testing the app yourself every day.
The second one is quantitative like
measure everything you can like is
retention fine is app closes fine uh
what's happening to your reviews. You
might have to make some trade-offs.
Ideally, you wouldn't, but
realistically, if you go from zero ads
to some amount of ads, there is some
risk that some curves might come down,
but I think you should know what that
cost is. Anyway, that's like through AB
testing, that's how we measured it to be
honestly, our retention was maybe a
slight hit, but mostly neutral for most
of our ad tests over time. Um, that's
one. The third one is there is of course
you go from a free product to selling
something. Users won't always say thank
you for doing that. Uh like this.
Imagine if Uber started completely free
and and one day they said okay now we're
going to charge for our Ubers. Users
would hate that too. And that was that's
kind of what we did. I mean in a way we
provided a free service and we kept a
lot of the elements free but we said hey
actually you can buy a streak repair now
and you might have to see an ad at the
end of your session. uh we got some
complaints. The thing that helped us
have clarity was one retent retention
was fine like retention was neutral on
most of these experiments and uh when
you looked at our community's complaint
volume if you quantify that for example
how we for per a million DAUs how many
ad complaints are there or ad negative
reviews what however you want to count
that versus other topics like for
example I realized uh this is I did this
quantitative analysis in 2016 because we
were at this pivot a moment of like do
we launch ads or do we not launch ads
and we looked at for example the number
of complaints about why we didn't have
the Finnish language on Dualingo was 3x
the number of people that are
complaining about Dualingo having ads so
that starts putting it into perspective
like it's not zero complaints but
actually in the grand scheme of things
this is not going to break the app and
our community is not going to run away
tomorrow so I think understanding the uh
the volume of what you're doing to the
community as much as you can. Gives you
a perspective. Otherwise, every negative
comment as a product builder hits home
really hard. Like everything looks like
the world is falling apart. That's why
it helps to like look at the broad
picture of like all of our issues as a
product and all products have many
issues.
>> Yeah, that that's exactly what I was
going to say is that it's so hard as a
builder.
>> It's really hard
>> to get those few negative reviews. And I
I think that's a really helpful insight
to look at that bigger picture and
understand like I I got a bunch of
negative reviews from my weather app for
the audacity of charging $40 a year for
a weather app [laughter]
and I did get probably overfocused on
those negative reviews. But then when
you look at all the people who were were
subscribing were staying subscribed
actually have pretty good retention.
It's like you got to like zoom out and
not let those like that small subset of
users who are going to complain tank
what's ultimately going to help drive
the business forward. How did you work
on ad quality? I believe you you
implemented ADM Mob um first time and
again I I in my weather app I had ADM
Mob eventually I I ended up pulling it
because it was like gambling ads with
like you know 777 and animations and
like all this crap. How did you work
with ADM Mob and how do you think about
ad quality as part of the experience and
how it can actually be detrimental to
the experience?
>> Yeah, I mean ad quality we
I would say we are like incredibly
strict on but with programmatic you of
course have some amount of control not
full control but with anything that is
honestly it could be even slightly
dicey. We blocked all those categories
like if it's gambling even if it's like
games that look kind of sketchy pick
your category. any of those that we
didn't feel was also young audience safe
and or just brand safe we blocked. So
the starting point is we used ADM mob
first and then we integrated other
sources like Facebook ads or at the time
flurry and and now we use also I think
multiple networks we use unity the that
was to mainly broaden demand but for
category and what kind of ads we allow
we tried our best to block off any
categories that are dicey even though it
might be a revenue loss we're like we
don't care the most more important thing
is good user experience and ad quality
so we did we did a lot of cate category
blocking and if we needed to do custom
blocking. We went and tried to work with
ad networks to be like this type of ad
has like three X buttons to exit. We
don't want this in our app. Please don't
give us this thing. So, we also did some
of that back and forth as well. That's
our stance this year. Also, to improve
ad quality, we're also doing our own
direct ads more and more because then we
control quality entirely. Like it's an
advertiser that we know like we shook
hands with and the format is what we've
created. So, it's beautiful and it's a
great advertiser. So, one now new lever
for us is to reduce programmatic volume
and increase direct volume because it's
just a better user experience.
>> Yeah, I I love what yall are doing. I
mean, it's hard for smaller apps who
don't have scale to do this kind of
thing, but tell me more about how these
partnerships work to improve that ad
quality so that it does improve the user
experience because you've been
incorporating Dualingo characters into
the ads with the brands you're
partnering with, right?
>> Have you seen them? It's
>> but I read about them.
>> It's very cool. uh it's currently only
in the US. So we're focusing on growing
these in the US because obviously we
created a great format, but to be able
to scale this, we also need to be
working with companies and right now
we're just focused on companies that
would want to advertise with us in the
US. We created multiple formats, but the
one I love the most and that seemed to
be working really well is one of our
characters. So we have eight Dolingo
characters on Dualingo that you see uh
is it introduces the ad. For example, uh
pick a brand. Let's say it's a
detergent. I'm making this up. It's not
like we we had exactly this, but uh one
of our characters, Lily, would make
jokes about like, oh, like I need to
wash my clothes. I wish I could do that.
And we kind of write a custom script to
introduce that ad that's very short and
then the ad itself plays so that at
least we are building a little bit of
our character world further and it's not
jarring as like you ended a lesson.
Right now, that's what our ads are
really a little bit where like you see
an ad, it feels like you're easing into
the ad. We're trying this right now.
It's when you see it as a user, it's
it's actually like a as an ad, it's a
very delightful format. Our challenge, I
would say, is scaling it. I think we
have since it's a custom format. Well,
you got to go up to advertise and
explain how this works. So, it's it's a
bit of a slow adoption process, but
we're going to I mean, our goal is to
basically increase the volume of these
ads and reduce the programmatic by a
good amount in 2026. One of the ads you
do often show is for the subscription
itself. How do you balance from an LTV
perspective and monetization
perspective? How do you balance when to
show those um ads for the subscription
and then when to show programmatic or
these new brand ads?
>> So we just to set the stage if you do a
Dualingo lesson and this includes any of
our lessons. So you could do language,
math, music, and chess. Uh, at the end
of that lesson, you see an ad, and we
decide, like you said, if we should show
you a programmatic ad versus a one of
our internal ads, which could be an ad
for a subscription, or it could also be
an ad for our other products like the
Dualingo English test, but we call those
basically internal ads that we decide
we've produced and it is a Dualingo
product. Majority of them are going to
be either super Duolingo ads or Dualingo
Max ads. The decision logic is mostly
now controlled by ML actually. But the
ML uses various signals that is trying
to figure out LTV maximization at its
core and it is looking at every signal
that we feed it that could be an
indicator for someone that is more
likely to buy super or it also balances
out of course like if for example it's
shown you the same it doesn't really
show you the same super ad three times
but if it's shown you super ad three
times uh that clearly you're not
interested in it backs off and shows you
other ads. Um, so it is basically built
to optimize LTV uh with a likelihood to
purchase being the objective function.
>> A lot of apps that have ads in them
don't do this kind of thing, but like as
cheap as the CPMs are these days, I
think all developers should be
experimenting with putting ads in for
the premium product. It's a perfect way
to kind of balance that monetization of
if you have a premium product and you're
not making that much on ads, which you
just don't. And actually I'll follow up
with a question there, [laughter] but um
uh but it's a great opportunity to like
remind people, hey, there is a paid
product. There is there are features you
can get and highlighting the benefits. I
I've seen quite a few of the ads early
in the journey when I was first using
Dualingo and they're really good. like
they really highlight well like hey
you're doing great but you can do even
better and they really highlight the
product features and so I think that's a
great opportunity for premium developers
who do have ads to be exploring that
more to kind of push that upgrade to the
subscription
>> 100% and I think the other reason I like
our ads is they're just better than
programmatic ads like a user
>> better user experience
>> it's just a better user experience I I
mean I think if I had a magic wand I'd
rather have no programmatic ads within
my app and only internally only produce
sets because they look better. And we're
also building kind of lore for our world
characters through even though they
might be talking about super, they're
also cracking jokes about their own. For
example, we have this kind of
controversial super ad. I don't know if
you've seen this one where Junior, one
of our characters, is in a bathroom
stall and he like peaks and like makes
like a roll joke because there's a
toilet roll that he's like peeking
under. It's kind of weird, but it's like
we're kind of also entertaining it a
little bit with the ads we produce cuz
we have produced them with that intent.
Yeah,
>> it's way better than showing
programmatic ads.
>> How how does ad monetization do per user
compared to subscription? And is there
and I I would assume part of the idea
with these partnerships and other things
you're working on is to continue pushing
that monetization better and better for
those free users.
>> So for us, if you look at Dualingo's
statistics, subscription revenue is far
and above the biggest chunk of our
revenue. So I think it's above above
80%. And ads is a much smaller
percentage. But if you look at payers
about among our DAU base actually MAU
base it's about 10%. So 10% of our users
subscribe. However, subscription is more
than 80% of our total revenue. So we
focus naturally when it comes to what we
think about for monetization mostly on
the subscription side of things because
uh we believe it has one much it's
already a much larger business but also
much higher potential because we still
feel like with any of these actually but
certainly still even with the
subscription that has now become a
sizable business there's just so much
more to do that is making the
subscription better and also with a
premium app you realize over time and
this is a lot of experimentation we've
done one is like building the product to
be better. So making our subscription
features more valuable. But there's a
lot of work to be done and also making
sure you can communicate those. Well, we
touched on videos. Videos certainly help
because that gives you a format where
you can actually say, "Hey, this other
thing that you could buy has all these
features because there's not a lot of
other easy places to tell that story. On
top of that, there's like how you design
your purchase pages make a difference.
For example, how users enter that enter
that flow makes a difference. So anyway,
that's in my head how you're
communicating your subscription. So
we're putting more and more of our
monetization energy into those pieces,
meaning make the subscription better and
more useful and make sure we can
communicate it well. That tends to have
higher return for us in general as a
business than ads. So most of our
efforts is on subscriptions.
>> Yeah. I mean, you know, Facebook's
numbers are just insane. And you know, I
think I saw like 250 per user per year
in the US, which is about what a do a
plus subscription costs. But the time in
app, the way they're able to do their
bid structures and things like that, but
I imagine there's still a lot of room to
grow. But it's interesting that at
Dualingo scale, the subscription
opportunity is still so much better than
the than the ad monetization.
>> I think so. And I think with social
media apps, the reality is it is fairly
easier I think as a product problem to
integrate ads into a feed. Uh and in a
product where users are there not for a
particular utility but they are there a
lot of times to to pass time or they
don't even know why they're there. So I
think it's way easier to increase ad
load in a way that is not disruptive to
how the user feels when you are there on
an app for a particular utility. And for
us, a lot of users are there to learn a
topic. Well, not a lot. All of our users
are there to learn something. I think
increasing ad load is not particularly
that tolerated, I guess. So, I think
that that creates a challenge for a
challenge and opportunity. Honestly, for
us, subscription just fits as a better
business model than increasing ad load
the way Facebook might be doing.
>> Yeah. One last question on ads and then
we'll move on to the subscription. But
um one of your the product managers on
your team came on the podcast I think 18
months ago and he talked about holdouts
that y'all do long-term holdouts. Did
y'all do a hold out on ads? Are there
people today is there like 0001% of of
subscribers that still don't have ads
that you can measure against the people
who do have ads?
>> Not anymore. But we did run I think
almost like a year or two year long hold
out for ads. Wow.
>> We do run long hold outs. Although I
don't recommend year-long holdouts
because what also eventually happens is
>> you forget that you have a hold out and
then eventually you introduce you're not
testing it every day you introduce a bug
to it. So like even though you have a
year-long hold out you realize at some
point you actually polluted it because
you like introduced bugs there anyway.
So very long hold outs we are anti just
because of a practical perspective but
we do weigh more like three month uh
six-month holdouts on things that we
know have different short to or we
assume will have short to long-term
effects that might be different. One of
those, for example, this is not exactly
monetization, but anything that has to
do with our leaderboards, we try to run
long period experiments or long holdouts
because uh on the Dualingo leaderboard
set, it if you start from the lowest
league, it takes you 10 weeks to get to
the highest one. If we change the
dynamics of how the leaderboard works,
we might not see the actual result in in
two weeks. So, we kind of let these run
for longer. Another one is push
notification experiments where every of
course new p push notification you
introduce has amazing returns because it
has amazing novelty but then if you wait
out 6 weeks sometimes it doesn't just
come back to neutral it actually turns
negative because you're sending too many
push notifications that turns people
off. So some stuff that we assume not
just monetization might have longer term
adverse effects. We run long hold outs
or just run a long experiment. the way
Duolingo tests things. We could talk
hours just on that, but I did want to
get back to the monetization journey.
So, at what point did it become clear
that you needed to introduce a
subscription? And this was pretty early
in the, you know, Apple famously opened
up subscriptions to all apps in 2016. I
believe you launched a subscription
pretty soon after that, 17.
>> So, what was the story from, okay, ads
are starting to work. We we haven't
pissed off all the users. [laughter]
Um but now we're gonna like actually
start charging.
>> So the the journey we went through was
ads was the first experiment and then
after ads was introduced uh as a good PM
I was reading every review that was
written on on Dualingo that included the
app store or Reddit or our own forums
and there was a significant amount of
people that are that were saying can I
please pay you guys? I don't want to see
ads and I love Dualingo. I get so much
value out of it. It wasn't like a
hateful I hate ads. It was more like I
would love to give you guys a few
dollars just to remove my ads. And we
thought that was a good idea. And
subscriptions were quite early for
mobile apps at the time. You're right.
Majority of the app wisdom was generally
you you want to sell IEPs and I think
games had obviously like kind of
popularized that and that was pretty
common. Subscription apps were earlier.
There was the big like streaming and
entertainment but outside of that there
wasn't a lot of digital subscription
behavior. So we took that idea to heart,
but we said we're not sure if the
subscription thing is for us. We were
our mind was still like is we probably
going to have an AP model. So we tested
an AP which was honestly like looking
back it's so janky and it's not clear
why people bought this but we said you
can buy an ad-free month of Dual. So for
30 days we'll turn off the ads but it's
a one-time purchase. And we tested
different price points. We tested $3,
$5, and $10. And everyone thought this
kind of wouldn't work. uh like it's like
why would people pay this one-off
bizarre exchange? Honestly, the update
was kind of good uh and way more than
what we expected. So, we were like
clearly there is some demand for turning
off ads. Even though we created the most
bizarre package to sell, people want to
buy this. Let's make it a subscription.
But to make it a subscription, just no
ads felt slim as a subscription service.
So then we built offline capabilities.
So, we said you can use Dualingo fully
offline and turn off your ads. And then
when we designed the purchase page,
we're like, this looks really weird with
two features. We need a third feature,
but we couldn't actually at the time
figure out what the third feature should
be. So, we kind of wrote a line there
that was the thing that users were
telling us, which is support Dualingo in
its mission of free education. I think
we just said support Dualingo's mission
for short. And that was our first entry
into subscription. That was Dualingo
Plus. And honestly, what I think we saw
happen was probably majority of users
early on bought it for the fact that
they enjoyed dueling us so much and
wanted to contribute back. The other
half or maybe the half of the demand was
from no ads and minimally for offline
and that was that kind of started us
giving us a run rate. Obviously, I mean,
I'm happy to talk about it more, but
from then to today, the subscription has
evolved a lot, but that was the very
first version.
>> Yeah, that's fascinating. And I I do
want to go through that journey. So that
is pretty light. I mean again this was
2017 so best practices and everything
else hadn't fully evolved and this was
just a experiment but how how did you
start evolving that over time? What were
what were some of the and maybe just
kind of give us the highlights of the
last almost decade now eight eight years
the kind of biggest unlocks when we
added this to the payw wall when we
added this new tier. What were some of
those big unlocks over the past 8 years
that really kind of moved the business
forward?
>> There's a few and let me try to think 10
years is a lot of time. There's a few
levers that have
>> looking back have really either caused
step function increases immediately or
over time it really compounded. So one
of them I guess now if you work in
subscriptions now this is like kind of a
no-brainer but at the time it really
wasn't. Having free trials is one. I
actually as a PM I resisted free trials
for a long time. I assumed it would like
completely flop. The
>> product was already free.
>> Yes, exactly. It's like why would people
want to try free trials for the exact
same product they've used for years? The
product is free. Like if we were a fully
premium product, free trial in my head
made a lot of sense, but for premium,
like you said, it didn't I thought it
didn't make sense. Turns out I was
wrong. Free trials are really helpful
for the obvious skeptic user that might
not want to pay upfront, but they are
interested in trying it out. It just
makes it so easy to just jump in and
try. It's very intuitive. Now, as a
user, I love free trials because I'm
like, well, I don't want to commit to
pay. Let me give it a go.
>> Were there specific things that were
then behind the payw wall that people
needed to experience?
>> Not really. I mean, offline you can say
offline, but it's
>> offline is the same as online. It just
works when you're in airplane mode. So
this this if you imagine this
subscription which is no ads and
offline, you didn't really need to
experience it, but I think it just
removes the payment hesitation. So it
lowers the barrier to entry. So you're
not committing payment. You're like,
I'll give it a go. And I think that's
the real benefit of free trials. So at
this point, we have
>> where we're very pro free trials. And I
think our purchase flows are now
designed to highlight how our free trial
works as a mechanic. We even have
designed pages which like communicate,
hey, there's a 7-day free trial on day
five. We're going to send you a
notification to see if you still want
your subscription. Like
>> because I and this has performed well in
AB tests because I think users have a a
subscription aversion and I think in a
lot of countries, maybe not as much the
US, there's also subscription scam
aversion where you click on something,
you somehow like can't get out. I think
if you highlight how what a free trial
is, one is like you don't have to pay
anything really. uh and out what the
mechanics of it, it relieves this
subscription aversion.
>> Yeah. Well, while we're on the topic, I
know you recently did an experiment with
a try for free button.
>> We've been experimenting with a lot on
everything uh our purchase pages and
maybe it's worth talking about. You
mentioned AB testing. Maybe I'll I'll
take on take us on a tangent for 10
seconds. So, Dualingo concurrently runs
somewhere around 400 AB tests. So the
Dualingo app itself is is heavily
evolving real estate and a good chunk of
those not majority but a good chunk of
them also happen on our purchase flow.
So if you look at any element whether
that's like Duo's flight path on the
super page or what the copy we write,
how it's highlighted, how it's
underlined, what the button color is,
what the button copy is, all of those
elements we have teams trying to figure
out how to make them better. And of
course for the record we're talking a
lot about monetization. That's not the
only place in the app where we're doing
this. Like our onboarding flow is the
same. Our session end is the same. Our
lessons are the same. So we take kind of
like maximal care into improving all
these flows, but modernization is no
exception. But that button copy we've
experimented a lot. And that is one
learning that I honestly didn't have or
didn't really expect. What you say in
the purchase button makes a massive
difference on your revenue curves. We
have tested many things. There's a
couple magic strings that were like you
look at the graph and you're like there
must be a measurement mistake like why
are the numbers so green the two
specifically were we went from I think
start my free trial so I think we said
something like uh subscribe uh that was
that that's your baseline and then we
tried many things but one of the big up
list was start my free trial that was
very good and then we tried what did we
say try for free that was better and
then we tried try for zero
0 0 uh weirdly that is the string that I
think hacks your brain to really grock
that that button is entirely free 0.0
like two decimals now I think that's
what's live in the app if I'm not
mistaken and that performed really well
>> and just changing try for free to try
for dollar sign 0.0 00 you saw a
meaningful uplift in conversion.
>> Correct. Yes.
>> And it was I guess the start trial
conversion but then also the the trial
conversion to pay. So like both numbers
went up.
>> Correct.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah.
>> So [laughter] crazy.
>> Yeah. It was unexpected honestly. It's
like you wouldn't think this makes that
much of a difference. I think one other
thing I've learned with fremium and
honestly any subscription and payroll
behavior is a lot of when you go and
design these flows you are designing
with logic right you are saying let me
communicate my features so whoever is
going to buy should read them and
understand what they're buying so they
can do the logical exchange or if I part
with this many dollars I will get this
many features that is how you go and
design a flow but the reality is humans
do not experience mobile flows that way
at all Actually, it's way more based on
emotion and reaction than, oh, let me
read and think about the value exchange
of what what is happening here. It's way
more emotional. So, I think these these
things that are kind of sound like, you
know, they're saying the same thing,
right? Zero. Zero and free are the same
thing, but they create different
emotions make a difference.
>> That's fascinating. Well, we've dived
down multiple levels of rabbit hole, but
[laughter] to surface us back up in
thinking through the past 10 years, were
there any other kind of key unlocks uh
specific features that you put behind
the payw wall that really move the
needle?
>> Definitely. So, uh we talked about free
trial. Another thing for us that was a a
quite a meaningful turn in our evolution
was honestly putting more useful
features behind our subscription. So I
started with saying okay we had ads and
offline. We started adding more we had
we added two features that were
basically transformational to the
subscription. One of them was Dualingo
had this pacing mechanic called hearts.
Now it's it's called energy but hearts
was not integrated with our subscription
at all. The way it works is you can you
you can go through Dualingo and do as
much as you please. But if you make a
certain number of mistakes, you start
running out of hearts and then before
you can do new content, you have to
regenerate hearts and you can do that by
doing practice lessons or you can do
that by watching ads or uh at the time
we said you can renew your hearts with
an inapp purchase. We decided to
integrate the hearts mechanic with our
subscription and said hey if you
subscribe you actually get unlimited
hearts. That was a big turning point
because turns out a lot of users don't
want to practice old content. They just
want to do new content. Even though
practice is good for your learning, we
said uh okay if you would like this is
you can choose your optionality if you
subscribe. That was a good turning point
because it made the feature set of plus
dualingo plus at the time way more
integrated and way more useful. Another
feature we created was again around
practice custom practice. So we created
a feature that is a separate tab called
practice hub. We we made that part of
super at the time. Actually it's now
became fully free. We now gave it all to
free users because we realized it should
be free. So we did that. But at the time
we said if you would like to do very
custom practice on the things you've
learned on Dualingo, here's an extra
place where that's a served to you as an
inventory. So you can go back and
practice anything you'd like in whatever
order you like rather than the order we
prescribe. Anyway, this is a very uh
long- winded way to say feature
improvements that expanded the feature
set of Dualingo Plus was naturally a win
on two fronts, both conversion and
retention of the subscription, which is
great. We love that and that gave us a
lot of scale. Other than that, honestly,
it is rare to have put like one silver
bullet that improved things for us. A
lot of this has been continuous AB
testing improvement. I think we talked
about the copy version as like one thing
but imagine that happening across every
bit and piece of our purchase flow and I
think that's why Dualingo's purchase
flows get copied a lot because I think
people have heard us say this I say this
a lot which is like we did AB test many
things. So if you want to copy something
probably you're copying something that
has been tested at least for Dualingo.
It probably won't work for most apps but
you can look at us because we've tested
stuff.
>> That's fascinating. Before we move on, I
I did want to talk one more angle of
monetization. I know by the time this
podcast airs, you'll have taken
something that was previously paid and
moving it into the free tier. Why? Why
do that?
>> So, let me talk about actually two
features that we one of them we just did
and we are about to do. So practice sub
I talked about we have realized
that number one as a goal we would like
to provide more value to our free users
because free users there's there's the
missionary reason why we want to teach
more people but there's the business
reason which is free users are our
marketing engine. Dualingo grows as a
entire user base and as a business
through word of mouth. Word of mouth is
much stronger if your free product is
stronger because you might or might not
pay irrelevant. If you're using
Dualingo, you tell your friends about
Dualingo and say, "This is awesome. I'm
learning Spanish." They try it, they do
the same. So that's how Dolingo really
grows. That's the majority of our growth
engine. And that growth engine of course
gets stronger if we can provide more
value to free users. So it's a it's a
delicate balance if you're a freedom
product to decide uh how much value to
put on each side, right? Um, and we
certainly want to put value as much as
possible to our free user base. So
that's the the overarching reason on on
why. Um, but the two features that we
did was practice hub and the second one
is explain my answer. These are really I
mean I I love these features uh because
they are really additive to your
dualingo experience. So practice hub we
talked about. I'm not going to repeat
it. That is now actually already live
with with free users. and uh explain my
answer is moving from being a dual max
feature which is our highest tier to to
free users because we have realized the
revenue value is not that high. So we
want to meaning it doesn't make that
much revenue.
>> How did you determine that?
>> We tested it. Uh [laughter]
we tested giving it uh for free and
compared it to a a a B condition or a
control condition where it is part of
max. the impact well there was impact
but we decided to kind of you know
reduce our revenue but rather provide
value for our free users because we
believe that's the right thing to do in
the long term and there's one more
reason which is when we first introduced
this feature it was financially
impossible for us to make it free
because it uses LLM calls to explain
basic what it does for the record is you
give an answer you answered something
and we basically use LLMs to to describe
to you what you got wrong for your
specific answer so it's very like
tailored. That's why there's an LLM that
that is used. LM costs were really high.
So, we had to put a part of a
subscription just to provide the
service. But costs have gone down
significantly and we've improved how we
cash things. So, since cost came down,
our only decision was revenue loss and
revenue loss we decided to take to
provide this on this service for
>> it seems like that's a a real theme is
being very strategic about what's free
and what's paid.
because of that balance because you want
to create that amazing free experience
but you still monetize and so that that
tension must be difficult as a product
team.
>> Yes. And you know honestly the hard the
hardest part is for me it's really easy.
I think for like CEO it's very easy. We
always want to do the right thing for
the user. It's not hard for us to think
about okay like how do we improve the
free experience? There's some obvious
things. The hardest part is taking a
loss in an experiment is not intuitive.
So the teams that are working on these
are finding it hard to be like I
understand all this good stuff you said
but we're going to drop our metric. It
it's like it doesn't feel intuitive. So
I think convincing the organ convincing
the teams and explaining why this is the
right thing to do long term is the hard
part because you can imagine the
positive side of what I'm saying doesn't
really have a metric but the cost of it
has a very real metric. So I think that
like they they run hand in hand, but I
think you have to realize if especially
if you're a premium business is if you
only always go by positive revenue
metrics, you will burn yourself to the
ground. Like uh I I don't want to call
out specific companies, but you can see
a lot of subscription businesses that
have effectively nickel and dime their
users if they're premium and then burn
their growth engine even though their
revenue kept growing. But that only
works for like some amount of years, but
eventually your growth stops. I think
for us, what's most important is our
growth engine, our user growth engine
keeps growing. That's why you have to
make these hard calls sometimes be like,
"We're going to take a loss. It's okay
because we're helping our growth engine
is is the convincing part is the hard
part.
>> How do those calls get made when an AB
test shows a benefit?" And I imagine
this happens in more than just these
like monetization features. But how do
you balance the kind of art of product
management against the science of
product management when you run 400
simultaneous AB tests?
>> This is a great question. I think this
happens a lot for us, I would say,
because we have this other side of our
equation as a business. So we talked
about user growth and monetization.
That's the same for every app. But
dueling is one more unique element which
is learning and learning efficacy. So we
run AB tests to try to improve our
learning efficacy. And the problem with
that is it doesn't have a single metric
you can put on a graph. Even if you
could, I mean we use proxy metrics.
There's no perfect metric for it. But
even if you have proxy metrics that are
going up, let's say your learning goes
up, but your revenue comes down. Should
you exchange that? Should you not
exchange that? There's these trade-offs
you have to make. And I think that's
where you move away from a mostly purely
science to like you said the art of
product management. How do these
decisions get made? if they are really
consequential it's like all right the
revenue loss might be large or there's a
DAU hit whatever it is like a clear
business hit we have to bring in most
senior people to decide if as a company
we should take this trade-off like that
means our CEO would be certainly
involved in saying okay committed let's
do this if it's at smaller scale I think
most of our teams understand these
trade-offs fairly well meaning they if
it's a exchange of for example clearly
the thing we're doing helps you improve
your conversation skills But in turn,
maybe it makes our content a little
harder. So maybe uh it hurts some of our
business metrics. But if the amount is
small, teams can independently make
those calls. If the magnitude is large,
but it's a strategic decision we should
make, then I think we bring in senior
people to sign off is kind of how we
operate.
>> And this is why Dueling is such a
well-loved app. I mean, hearing you
explain that and understanding how many
product decisions have been made over
the years to provide that better
experience at the expense of DAOU or
monetization or other things. It's why
people love it. And that's like you
said, you it's hard to put a metric on
that love and the social sharing and the
the feeling a user gets when they open
the app, but like it sounds like that's
something you protect very carefully as
a company, which then pays dividends
over the over the much longer term, even
if you can't always AB test your way to
that.
>> That that's very well said. We have this
operating principle that we I I love and
we repeat a lot is take the long view.
Meaning you can make business decisions
very differently if your goal is to be a
very profitable or a very fast growing
company for two years versus if you want
to build a company for that will be
around in 100 years. I think those are
like very different decisions and to be
specific. You could monetize the
Dualingo feature set very heavily if you
wanted to and for two years you'll make
a lot of money but one that's not our
goal and two that would be terrible for
free users but three we will burn
ourselves to the ground if we do that.
Like we cannot build a 100red-year
business by taking more and more from
that's what a lot of premium apps fall
into this premium trap where like the
easiest win you can always do is like oh
yeah let me take some free if you just
make it paid and immediately all your
metrics are green and that does kind of
work for 6 months or maybe a year but
eventually it stops working. The other
thing it does is it creates opportunity
for someone else to do it for free. The
Dualingo story, the very early one that
we didn't really talk about is why
Duelingo grew so much early on. At the
time, there were tools teaching
languages. There were the Rosetta Stones
of the world, but they were paid and
expensive. So, being free and fun
created a massive differentiator. If we
were to tomorrow wake up and say, "All
right, we're going to charge for all of
our great features." Very likely in two
years another great app, we'll do it for
free. So I think preserving the free
value is just a moat that we have to
keep and we want to keep for missionary
reasons but for business reasons it also
makes a lot of sense.
>> Yeah that such a great answer. Um well I
did want to move on to the new products
that Dualingo has been introducing and
kind of becoming a multi-product company
for a lot of apps. It it's a big leap.
The most famous example is Calm finding
sleep stories and that secondary product
market fit being this new lever of
growth that that really moved the needle
for them. So tell me about why you
decided to start adding new courses and
we can talk through like how that went
and what you added and everything.
>> Definitely. It's it's honestly it's been
a really fun journey and it's been now
has it been four years since we
introduced our new subject. Maybe three
to four. Um, but now we have math,
music, and chess on top of languages.
The reason we chose those those uh those
specific subjects, they're all varied
and they have their own thesis, but at
its core, they have a few properties
that carry across. One is they could be
taught on mobile in a fun way. Not every
topic qualifies. For example, coding we
considered, but it's really hard to
teach on mobile, so we decided not to
invest there. That doesn't mean we won't
ever do it, but today it felt too hard
to do. Uh, another one is they all have
large markets of people that are already
learning these subjects. So, we're not
trying to create the market necessarily,
but we are there's already existing
demand. That's two. And three, and I
think this is connected to mobile, our
expertise in language, which is at its
core, if you think about it, a
bite-sized fun experience, can carry
over fairly well to these subjects. The
anti-example of this would be stuff that
is done offline. Like running could have
been something we decided to do, but
that is an offline experience that you
tie with an online experience. That is
not exactly how we're used to doing
bite-siz exercises. So, we wanted to
make sure our competencies played well
in these subjects. So, these topics fit
really well. We actually looked around
quite a bit before we invested in each
of them. the the maybe the fourth
internal reason these topics is each of
them had one or more people inside the
company that were quite tenured like
tenured builders that really wanted to
build these so they became kind of the
seed for these projects
>> so I did want to get into the staging of
this because you first launched math as
a separate app right so what was the
thesis behind doing that and then what
didn't work out that you now brought it
back into the app
>> yes our thesis changed actually over
time. So when we launched math, we
assumed our future would be separate
apps like our strategy we because at the
time we also actually had we still do
but we had another app called Dualingo
ABC that is meant to teach literacy to
younger children. So teaching their
first language rather than second
language that Duolingo teaches but our
strategy was headed in a direction where
all these new topics would be separate
apps. We thought at the time, this is
partly true still, but our our thinking
certainly evolved, that different
audiences would seek different apps
rather than be in one mega app for
multiple topic learning. So, if you
wanted to learn math, we thought the
overlap between you and the language
learner would be slim. And that's why
you would probably want a separate app
for doing one job. And I don't know if
this was common with them at the time,
but it felt really good as a strategy.
We have we did realize one thing as time
went on which is u actually two
realizations happened. One turns out a
lot of people want to learn multiple
things at once at least dualingo
learners want to learn multiple things
at once. So it became an inconvenience
actually to switch between apps and and
for two apps maybe you could survive but
if it's three four apps you're just not
going to do it. And there's just this
inherent human demand that we realize
exists within Dualingo which isn't just
like I'm here to learn
Spanish. There's certainly a lot of
users that are there for one thing, but
also a lot of users are there for
self-improvement in general. So, it was
a natural behavior that we just saw
happening, which is I'll learn a little
bit of math. I'll learn a little bit of
chess. I am there to spend my good
screen time on Dualingo to improve
myself. It is less relevant exactly what
that topic is. That might change over
time as long as I'm improving myself in
something
that lend like kind of led us towards
well, let's make it easy for these folks
to do that. Um, so that that was one.
The other one is just the business
realities of growing a separate app is
extremely expensive. While we were like,
why are we playing hard mode when we can
play easy mode? Because in the same app,
you have a user base. It's way easier to
get a user that is in the main app to
try something new than get them to
download an entirely new app.
>> It's so crazy to hear that from you. I
mean of all the companies with you know
tens of millions of users and beloved
and everything else that the separate
app was hard mode.
>> It's hard mode for sure and I think a
lot of companies have come to this
conclusion. I think there's successful
and unsuccessful examples of both of
these actually but the the famous
examples are I think Uber and Facebook
have done both separate and combined
apps in multiple forms. And that's why
that I don't think there's a right
answer for every company, but for us
this if you think about user behavior,
which is generally there's a lot of
users that are around self-improvement
and let me learn something and that will
change over time. It just made sense for
them to be in in one app.
>> Yeah. How did you solve the product
problem? I think you know one of the
challenges
of mobile is that you have such tiny
real estate to communicate everything to
shoehorn a feature into this tiny space
that's already crowded by other things.
How how did you solve the product
problem of it?
>> A lot of with a lot of work is the short
answer. And before we launched anything,
these projects all took probably from
six like somewhere from 6 to 12 months
to go from the first idea to full
launch. So that means in the meantime,
we probably designed, tested,
prototyped, redesigned, prototyped,
tested again on ourselves and some beta
users maybe many, many times until we
got to the state where it's like, okay,
within the confines of this mobile
experience, this feels fun enough. it's
actually teaching something useful and
it's good enough to go in the app and be
on par with the quality of where the
language courses are because language
courses have been improving for 13 years
whereas this new thing is starting from
scratch. So anyway, a lot of dog fooding
and prototyping I think is answer number
one. Um but the other one is I think you
can eventually teach a lot of things on
mobile. There's some courses that are
easy, there's some courses that are
harder. Music is really hard. I would
say chess is fairly easier because you
have you have one visual element that is
the chessboard as long as you fit that
into the mobile experience. You can
build a lot of stuff on it, but really
it's now contained. Music is way harder
because we're for example teaching you
piano skills on a screen and we have to
think a lot more creatively on how to do
that. And you can imagine the amount of
like stuff we've tried and still are
trying to improve which is you can't fit
an entire keyboard on a piano for
example. And you also can't fit it when
the phone is vertical. you have to turn
it horizontal to fit more key space. We
actually tilted the keyboard a little a
few degrees so it gives you a bit more
angle for touch space. So all that stuff
is like innovation that you end up
having to figure out. And I would say
music is the hardest. Chess is chess and
math are easier cuz math follows a very
similar visual style to in in exercises
language. How do you surface it to users
in the app in a way that doesn't get in
the way of the people who just want to
learn a language or are just there for
music or you know the the crowding the
screen real estate with these multiple
things. How how do you solve that
problem?
>> We've made it fairly integrated so it
doesn't feel like you are crossing into
a different app but it feels like you
are just switching what you're learning.
So we had already built a system
basically to switch courses. So if you
were learning Spanish, you could switch
to learn French or Italian, any other
language in that system. We now also
offer with some different hierarchy of
course unlike you could switch to French
which is the second language you learn
the most or there's your other topics
now which are math, music and chess. We
integrated there and honestly it's
worked fairly well because we do already
have a lot of users that learn multiple
uh languages per day and they started
discovering it. We also did some light
promos just to raise awareness on the
topics. That said, this remains a bit of
an unsolved problem if I'm being honest,
which is a lot of our users have no idea
that we also teach math, music, and
chess. So, next year, we're still going
to try to figure out how to make sure
that at least our our user base that's
coming to the app every day is aware
that these topics exist.
>> Yeah, it's a tough tough problem. How do
you think about competition with
Dualingo? Um, do you think of YouTube
and Netflix and other screen time as
competition or who who competes with
Duolingo?
>> I think any screen time is probably our
realistic competition. If you think
about the natural idea of competition,
you would probably think, well,
education, any education app, but
realistically
one, we are already way bigger than any
education app. So, at least user base
wise. So we don't particularly see
behavior of oh I stopped using Duolingo
and now I'm using an education app. Most
of any churn or any user that we lose
goes to spend time on Instagram or
YouTube or anything that is fun in in
their phone. So for us I think real
competition is good screen time
>> or I guess good or bad. I think that's
subjective but anything that is spent in
screen time is Duolingo's competition
and that's inherently why we spend so
much time on making Duolingo fun. Yeah,
>> it is also I would say it's headwinds to
try to take something that is brain
intensive like learning a language is
not an easy activity. It's not as
passive as scrolling on your feed. It's
actually like burning your brain a
little bit if you do it for a long time.
And we try to make it as easy as fun
because otherwise well you'll go to
Instagram, you'll go to Tik Tok. There's
many engaging things that are just
pulling you. So that's how it if I'm
being honest, we don't really think
about competition because it's so weird
to think about screen time. But if you
were to like define it, it's really
screen time. And
>> I think that's honestly the case for
most apps these days, unless it's a
specific utility where you need to like
get in, get out, solve a very specific
problem. If it's any kind of even habit
forming app, I mean, almost any app when
you launch your home screen, are you
pulled to Instagram or are you pulled to
Duolingo to do your lessons? and and it
it's tough. How do you think of AI as
competition? And will AI just subsume
everything? Nobody learns a language
because they've got their AirPods
automatically translating? Uh I imagine
that's a hot topic right now.
>> Well, I get this question a lot and I
actually really love it because I think
we have a pretty clear thesis uh with
with two parts of this question. So one
part is will AI remove the need for
learning languages and in that case will
Dolingo well what will Dualingo do if
that happens. The other one is I think
will AI disrupt Dualingo because AI has
language teaching capabilities. I'll
start with the first one. I think the
reality is
being able to teach a language is not
particularly a new part of a new ability
for a tool to have. What I mean by that
is textbooks also can teach you a
language. Now AI can which is for a
technology perspective it's incredibly
impressive. It can do that but text it
is not enough unfortunately to uh remove
the need to learn languages. People
we've learned and I'm only talking about
languages. We can talk about other
subjects that the reason people learn
languages incredibly varied. So you
might be learning to connect with your
heritage. AI doesn't really solve that
at the end. You still will want to learn
languages. This is similar to when
calculators came out. We didn't stop
teaching math. It's quite similar. So,
and and the need to learn languages does
not disappear even if you have massively
good simultaneous translation and AI can
do that really well. So, that's I think
we don't see language learning demand
going anywhere and we certainly don't
see it post LLMs either. The other
question is there are now other tools
that are non-dualingo like the chat GPTs
of the world that can actually teach you
language. If you ask it to teach me
Spanish, it will do something. And I
think that's that's very fair. But I
think that my textbook analogy still
applies there where it can teach you a
language, but is it exciting? Uh is it
fun enough? And until that is the case,
a thing being able to teach you a
language is not a threat to our
business. I think we don't see that
much. We continue investing in making
things fun for that reason. And maybe
the third thing I will add is we see AI
only as an accelerant to Dualingo
because we use AI to do mainly two
things that make Dolingo better. One
produce content at scale at higher
quality and higher volume. The other one
is introduce features that we couldn't
do before that solves some of the
teaching problems that we really care
about solving like conversation
practice.
>> Yeah. So in a way AI has helped us a lot
and I think it will continue to and we
will continue building better products
with AI. So we're we're happy in
everything that's happening. Well let's
move on to a few of your uh contrarian
takes. So don't build for a persona
build for the general population. Why? I
mean it's the classic PM thing. Build a
persona. Figure out who you're talking
to. All that kind of stuff.
>> Yeah. This is any PM PMwork would say
don't build for a general audience.
Always pick who you're building for. I I
think when building consumer products at
least this is certainly dualingo. I
don't want to generalize too much but we
have we we are like very anti-persona.
So if someone comes in from the outside
world joins our team most of the time
they their instinct is like oh yeah like
I'm going to build some persona maps.
I'm going to call this person the
wanderer the other one the explorer and
which one am I going to build for? And
we're immediately like please don't do
that. like stop because I think if you
want it really depends on what kind of
product you want to build. If you're
trying to get to a billion users, which
we we have kind of the the the ambition
to you, you have to eventually build for
a general population. That's that's
that's like I think my theory number
one. Theory number two is with language
learning, if you pick a persona, you're
actually really cutting off the rest of
your audience. And language learning is
such a long tale of reasons for
learning. Someone could be learning to
get a job. Someone to be learning to
move countries. Someone could be
learning to connect with their heritage.
These are extremely varied. So if you
pick one and say, "Oh, this is really
important." Yeah. Like the common PM
framework would say that's how you
succeed. I think for us that's how you
fail because then you've ignored
basically the entire longtail of why
people are learning languages and you've
built for a very specific one. So if the
use case of a product is varied, which a
lot of consumer products have that
property actually, uh you have to figure
out how to build for the general
population.
>> That's great. Uh next one, people don't
read.
>> Okay, this is another favorite one. This
kind of connects to something I hinted
at. Most early career or honestly even
who people who join dueling with
experience product designers or PMs fall
into this trap of what they write on the
screen as copy and text think is read by
the user. Um the reality is on mobile
apps people's attention span is already
shrunk. It's like you might be like
cooking with one hand and doing your app
with the other hand. You might be on the
toilet. There's all kinds of situations
where now your attention span is like
shrunk. And the other reason is you are
kind of going through an experience by
not kind of paying attention to every
detail but the core maybe like the 30%
of a screen. So we always repeat this.
Of course it's an exaggeration. Of
course people read some things on mobile
but really in a graphical it interface
they read very little. But to simplify
my like extreme hot take is people don't
read. So don't rely on text rely on
great design to guide the user. And
maybe the a better said version of this
is if you need to write a tutorial on
what to do, you've already lost it. So
it needs to be design that leads the
user, not the text and the labels that
you wrote.
>> Yeah. All right. Well, let's close out
with the three questions I ask every
guest. What was the most impactful
experiment change or something you
implemented this year? Your biggest win?
>> It's not exactly this year. It's been
two years, but this is worth calling is
the introduction of video call on
Dualingo. I've been using Dualingo to
improve my Spanish for nine years now.
And this is the one feature I can
confidently say it's helped me speak
Spanish way more than before. And I
mean, we're very excited for what it can
do. It's it still feels very early, but
it already if you use it, you can just
speak Spanish better. And I feel great
about that.
>> That's such a great example of building
a truly great product experience with
AI. a lot of people are slapping it on
and you know trying to put a chatbot in
their app where it doesn't make sense
and the video call with Lily is such a
great example of taking this new
technology and actually creating a great
customer experience and it's cool that
you brought that up as such a win.
>> What about the biggest fail? biggest
fail is this is not I don't think this
went very public but actually what uh a
lot of our community doesn't remember or
don't know is before video call our
first attempt at like a big speaking
feature was a human-based tutoring
product so it was a higher tier
subscription because it was quite
expensive for us to logistically provide
but you would press a button I think we
called it did we call it tutors but it
was our higher tier subscription but you
would press a button you would connect
with a Spanish tutor on demand. No
booking required. Honestly, it was
pretty awesome. Uh like for speaking
practice, it was really awesome. It had
this one massive problem which is uh no
one wanted to do it. [laughter]
It was really scary. Uh Duelinga,
imagine this super fun experience and we
would tell you, hey, you are going to
connect with a human. You're going to
practice Spanish. People would press it.
They would dial in. and we would see
their faces come online and they were
like, "Oh get me out of here."
Because one, it's really scary to speak
in Spanish, like on the on the language
that you're learning. And two, there's
another real human on the other side.
That was extremely jarring. We iterated
a lot to ease you into it. But
eventually, we gave up because humans
just did not want to do that. And
actually, there's this brings me to
another hot take that I do want to
mention. Do not take user feedback at
face value. for years. This is what
people as they asked us to build. Like
we're like, "Please build me a system
where I can talk to a human tutor." We
built it. No one used it.
>> It's such a great example of of a great
feature, but just it doesn't work. And
like as product people, we can still get
into our heads, take feedback, and build
something that's truly great, but it
doesn't work. So that's that's such a
great one. All right, last question. uh
growth would be easier if
>> I think growth would be easier
if two things were true. One is pixel
perfect design didn't matter in consumer
because I think consumer app design bar
has become so high that if you want to
make progress and lead productled growth
you have to get pixel perfect design
that will go out to users. can't be just
a wireframe looking button that you put
in your app or your illustration is like
not really cared for. It this increases
the time to ship products. So that's one
pixel perfect design does matter and it
growth would be way easier. Maybe this
was the case when apps first came out.
Uh but it matters and it makes a
difference. And I think too if AI really
contributed to productivity in both
prototyping and coding and what I mean
by that is I think we are seeing today
in the ranges of 10 to 20% productivity
improvements. That's really impressive.
But like when LLMs first came out, my
hope was that they would be kind of 10x
improvers. And I think if you look at
the Silicon Valley hype today, that's
what the messaging is. But really, I'm
looking at what we're doing and what
every company is doing. Really, the
speed up of the product pipeline is in
the 10 to 20% range. Growth would be
easier if we got what was promised and
it was 200% improvement, but I don't
think that's the case.
>> All right. Well, as we wrap up, anything
else you wanted to share? any uh any
jobs you wanted to shout out or
anything?
>> I will definitely do that. We are
currently hiring for honestly we're
always hiring but currently we're hiring
for quite a bit of product manager
positions. I think the audience of this
show probably is interested in
monetization since we also talked about
it and we're also hiring for
monetization product managers. They're
all on our creators web page.
>> Nice. Yeah, I think that would be a
great job for for this audience. So if
you're uh really into sub, you're
probably really into to monetization.
So, uh, uh, apply. All right, Jim, it
was so much fun talking to you today.
Thank you so much for joining me.
>> Thank you so much for having me. This is
awesome. [music]
>> Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.
[music]